Guide to the Ludlow Griscom papers, 1918-1961.
Griscom, Ludlow papers, 1918-1961.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ludlow Griscom papers, 1918-1961.
2701
Ludlow Griscom, 1890-1959.
11 cubic ft.
Correspondence, financial statements, meeting minutes, bulletins, field notes, reports, papers, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence concerning activities at the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University, as well as field notes, reports, and biographical information about Griscom.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ludlow Griscom, an ornithologist, was Research Curator of the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence concerning activities at the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University; letters of contemporary ornithologists, including Arthur A. Allen, Peter Paul Kellogg, Roger Tory Peterson, and Louis Agassiz Fuertes; requests for books published by the museum; and bird identification questions from professional and amateur ornithologists. Also, personal letters from family and friends; correspondence and related material concerning the American Defense Program at Harvard, which Griscom directed,1940-1945; correspondence, financial statements, minutes, annual reports, and bulletins of UNESCO (1948-1950); the Massachusetts Audubon Society (1938-1959); Massachusetts Department of Conservation, Division of Fisheries and Game (1947-1949); National Audubon Society (1932-1958); American Ornithologists Union (1922-1957); and the Boston Society of Natural History (1937-1954). Also includes material concerning the Mount Washington Observatory, the Children's Museum, and conservation topics. Also included are field notes, reports, biographical information about Griscom, and articles and papers by Griscom and other ornithologists.
Ludlow Griscom's pipe, Charvos drafting compass and an E. Faber pencil with holder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Griscom, Ludlow, 1890-1959.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964.; Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1874-1927.; Kellogg, Peter Paul, 1899-; Peterson, Roger Tory, 1908-; American Ornithologists' Union.; Boston Society of Natural History.; Children's Museum of Boston.; Harvard University. American Defense Program.; Harvard University. Museum of Comparative Zoology.; Massachusetts Audubon Society.; Massachusetts. Division of Fisheries and Game.; Mount Washington Observatory.; National Audubon Society.; Unesco.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources.; Ornithology.; Ornithologists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Field notes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1922-1933 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1934-June 1938 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, July 1938-1943 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1944-1948 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1954-1961 (Box 6)
- Financial correspondence of the Museum of Comparative Zoology (Box 6)
- Reports of the research curator (Box 6)
- Undated correspondence (Box 6)
- Massachusetts Audubon Society correspondence, 1938-1959 (Box 6)
- Massachusetts Audubon Society finances, 1947-1950 (Box 6)
- Massachusetts Audubon Society minutes, 1947-1950 (Box 6)
- Massachusetts Audubon Society bulletins, November 1936-December 1936; 1943 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, Nature Protection Minutes, 1948 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, 2 articles of H.J. Coolidge, 1948-1949 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, 7th Pacific Science Congress Bulletin, February 1949 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, General Conference Bulletin, June 1950 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, Bulletin #12, Science in UNESCO, December 14, 1949 (Box 6)
- UNESCO, Miscellaneous material (Box 6)
- Division of Fisheries correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 6)
- Division of Fisheries finances and annual report, 1947-1949 (Box 6)
- Division of Fisheries minutes, November 1948-October 1949 (Box 6)
- Commonwealth of Massachusetts - Conservation Acts, Nos. 31-1276, 1949 (Box 6)
- Division of Inland Fisheries Progress Report, Dec. 1947 (Box 6)
- Wildlife Research-Pheasant Stocking in Massachusetts, April 1946 (Box 6)
- Wildlife Research - Pheasant Stocking in Massachusetts, A Survey in U.S. (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous conservation material (Box 6)
- Mt. Washington Observatory, minutes and notes (Box 6)
- Mt. Washington Observatory, financial reports (Box 6)
- Mt. Washington Observatory, annual report, June 1950 (Box 6)
- Mt. Washington Observatory, 6th quarterly progress report, 1950 (Box 6)
- Children's Museum reports (Box 6)
- First Draft of 1957 U.S. Department of Interior National Park Service (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous papers, reports, brochures (Box 6)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Typewriter rental papers (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Newspaper subscription papers (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Newspaper control sheets (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Foreign language group interpreters, readers, etc. (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Foreign language group methods and procedures (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Instructions to readers (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Foreign language press in New England (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Census reports (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Radio broadcasting Research Project (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, German techniques of propaganda by Ludlow Griscom (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Interviews by Ludlow Griscom (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Spanish Library information (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Progress Reports of the program (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Washington Reports, March 24, 1942-October 1943 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Scandinavian Press, 1942 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Yiddish, Latin American, French and Greek Nationality, Czechoslovakian Press (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Portuguese Press (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Polish and Hungarian Press (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Greek Press, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, German Press (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, French Press, January 1942-July 1943 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Italian Press, December 1941-1943 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Irish-American Press, 1943 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Finnish Press (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Correspondence, January 1940-1945 (Box 7)
- American Defense Program at Harvard, Undated and miscellaneous material (Box 7)
- National Audubon Society correspondence, 1932-1958 (Box 8)
- National Audubon Society financial statements, 1941-1942; 1949-1950 (Box 8)
- National Audubon Society booklets on by-laws, 1935; 1944 (Box 8)
- National Audubon Society committee minutes and notes, February 1941-August 1956 (Box 8)
- National Audubon Society field notes, vol. 10, no. 6 (Box 8)
- National Audubon Society miscellaneous material (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union correspondence, 1922-1957 (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union minutes of annual meetings, 1940-1955; 1958 (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union financial reports, 1940-1942 (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union membership list, 1953 (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union 71st meeting report, 1954 (Box 8)
- American Ornithological Union miscellaneous and undated material (Box 8)
- Boston Society of Natural History correspondence, 1937-1954 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History minutes, 1939-1950 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History reports, 1945-1949 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History membership lists, 1949-1950 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History financial statements, 1938-1950 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History progress reports, 1946-1949 (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History brochures re Society (Box 9)
- Boston Society of Natural History miscellaneous and undated material (Box 9)
- Reports by Ludlow Griscom
  - Ratings of Warblers (Box 9)
  - Old World Warblers, Gnatcatchers and Kinglets (Box 9)
  - Woodhewers and Weavers' Finches (Box 9)
  - Family Tyrannidae (Box 9)
  - White-collared Seedeater and Tanagers (Box 9)
  - Crows and Jays, Shrikes, Mockingbirds and Thrushes (Box 9)
  - Blackbirds, Troupials and Meadowlarks (Box 9)
  - Rusty-crowned Ground Sparrows (Box 9)
  - Evening Grosbeak and Finches, Buntings and Sparrows (Box 9)
  - Yellow-faced Grassquit and Wrens (Box 9)
  - Papers on Grebes with mss., Loons with mss., Family Alcidae (Box 9)
  - Sounds made by birds (Box 9)
  - Notes on Willets (Box 9)
  - Thrushes and Black Duck (Box 9)
  - Field notes re Birds seen on Martha's Vineyard (Box 9)
  - Paper on "The Techniques of Field Ornithology" with mss. (Box 9)
  - Notes on South American Warblers, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Birds seen at Martha's Vineyard by others (Box 9)
  - Alabama State Bird Calls (Box 9)
  - Nicaraguan Report (Box 9)
  - Panama collecting trip with mss. (Box 9)
  - Costa Rica collection trip with mss. (Box 9)
  - "Additions to the Ornithology of Honduras," mss. with correspondence (Box 9)
  - Notes on birds (card form): Guatemalan (?) Furnariidae (Box 9)
  - Griscom and Sprunt: Warbler Study Draft (Box 10)
  - Cape Cod census, 1950 (Box 10)
  - Griscom et al: Mexican Checklist Project with correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 10)
  - South Texas Winter Season, 1954-1955 (Box 10)
  - Original Data: Concord book (field notes) (Box 10)
- Griscom articles, etc.
  - Elementary Biology in Modern Universities (Box 10)
  - Birds in Flight (Box 10)
  - The Changing Seasons - Summary of Fall Migration and Nesting Seasons (Box 10)
  - The Future of Our Waterfowl Abundance (Box 10)
  - Passenger Pigeon (Box 10)
  - Historic Developments of Sight Recognition (Box 10)
  - Eskimo Curlews (Box 10)
  - Wise Use of Sight Records (orig. mss.) (Box 10)
  - Population Studies of North American Birds (Box 10)
  - Order Colymbiformes (Box 10)
  - Order Gouiiformes (Box 10)
  - Suborder Alcae (Box 10)
  - Ranges (Box 10)
  - Orig. mss.: American Woodcock-Philohela Minor (Gmalin); Shore-birds (Suborder Charadrii); Wildlife Institute Paper and Data; Untitled miscellaneous mss., field and bird notes (Box 10)
- Other writings
  - Fred Packer's Book, draft, 1947 (Box 10)
  - Fred Packer's Book, draft, parts I and II, 1950 (Box 10)
  - William Brewsters Articles, 1875-1901 (Box 10)
  - Records of New England Birds (published material), June 1958-September 1958 (Box 10)
- Pamphlets and reprints
  - Press Review - U.S. Army American Expeditionary Forces, General Staff, No. 1-473, 1917-1919 (Box 11)
  - James B. Conant, A Chaple Talk, delivered by President Conant at the Opening of the Fall Term, 1945-1946 (Box 12)
  - James B. Conant, Speaking as a Private Citizen, January 1941 (Box 12)
  - James B. Conant, The Present Danger, February 7, 195119 (Box 12)
  - James B. Conant, Academic Patronage and Superintendence (Harvard University and Graduate School of Education), June 1938 (Box 12)
  - Yearbook of the Rhinebeck Bird Club, 1921 (Box 12)
  - "Ten-All Day Censuses from Duchess County, New York," Maunsell S. Crosby (two copies, one with notes on the inside back cover - The Wilson Bulletin, September 1925 (Box 12)
  - Supplementary Notes on the Birds of Dutchess County, N.Y., M.S. Crosby (Box 12)
  - "Two New Geographic Races of Birds from Central America," Alexander Wetmore (Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington) (Box 12)
  - "Three New Birds from the Yucatan Peninsula," Raymond A. Paynter, Jr. (Postilla Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History) (Box 12)
  - Common Sense in Common Names, Ludlow Griscom, September 1947 (Box 12)
  - "Mammals of Honduras," George G. Goodwin (Bulletin of American Museum of Natural History), May 1942 (Box 12)
  - Die Vogel Der Osterreichischen Costa Rica - Expedition Dr. M. Sassi (Leiden, E.J. Brill) (Box 12)
  - "Notes on a Samll Collection of Birds form the Republic of Honduras," H.G. Deigan, (The Auk), April 1936 (Box 12)
  - "The Distribution of Bird Life in Guatemala," Von Frtiz Heilfurth (Vogelleben in Guatemala, Museum of Zoology, Berlin) (Box 12)
  - Faculty Club of Harvard University, Articles of Association and Rules and Regulations (revised Edition), July 1933 (Box 12)
  - American Fern Journal (Quarterly of American Fern Society), April 1935-June 1935 (Box 12)
  - "Three Days of Botanizing in Southeastern Virginia," M.L. Fernald and Ludlow Griscom (Rhodora), April 1935-May 1935 (Box 12)
  - Critical Notes of Rare Panama Birds," L. Griscom (Boston Society of Natural History), February 1935 (Box 12)
  - "The Ring-Necked Duck as a Transient in the Northeastern States," Ludlow Griscom (The Auk), April 1939 (Box 12)
  - "A Statement for a Sub-committee of the Committee on Foreign Relations of the United States Senate - A Plan for Peace," Greenville Clarke, June 1950 (Box 12)
  - Kirkland House, Information and Rules, 1951-1952 (Box 12)
  - The Deacon's Testament, for Kirkland House, Harvard University, 1946 (Box 12)
  - Second Annual Report - Pacific Science Board, 1948 (National Research Council) (Box 12)
  - "Handwritten Notebook - Expedition to Yucatan (1927), Guatemala (1930), Honduras and Gutemala (1951)" Mss. Vol, August 1930 (Box 12)
  - Laws Relating to Game and Inland Fisheries, 1948 (Commonwealth of Massachusetts, Department of Conservation) (Box 12)
  - Directory - Department of Conservation 1949 (Commonwealth of Massachusetts) (Box 12)
  - "Accounts of Nicaragua Trip," (Mss. Vol.), February 11, 1917-April 16, 1917 (Box 12)
  - "Accounts of Nicaragua Trip," (Mss. Vol.), April 18, 1917-June 10, 1917 (Box 12)
  - The Deacon's Testament, for Kirkland House, Harvard University, 1947 (Box 12)
  - The Deacon's Testament, for Kirkland House, Harvard University, 1948 (Box 12)
  - The Rights and Responsibilities of Universities and Their Faculties (Association of American Universities), March 24, 1953 (Box 12)
  - "Statements by the Harvard Corporation in regard to Ass't. Prof. Wendell H. Furry, Teaching Fellow Leon J. Kamin and Assistant Prof. Helen Deane Markham", May 20, 1953 (Box 12)
  - "Birds of Linares and Geleana, Nuevo Leon, Mexico," George Miksch Sutton and Olin Sewall Pettingill, Jr. (Occasional Papers of the Museum of Zoology, Louisiana State University), November 22, 1943 (Box 12)
  - "Freedom at Harvard," An Exchange of Letters by Frank B. Ober of Baltimore, President Conant, and Greenville Clark, Fellow of Harvard College (Harvard Alumni Bulletin), June 25, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Louisiana Road Map (Box 12)
  - Mapa De Los Caminos Para Automoviles En Guatemala, Julio Alberto Rubic, 1928 (Box 12)
  - Map of Panama (Rand McNally), 1913 (Box 12)
  - Map of Panama (American Geographic Society of New York), 1928 (Box 12)
  - Map of the Republic of Nicaragua (W.M. Bradley and Sons) (Box 12)
  - Road Map of Jamaica (Jamaica Automobile Association), 1926 (Box 12)
  - Harvard Services, for Officers Employees and Departments (Harvard University Press), October 1, 1952 (Box 12)
  - Bird Check List of Southeastern Texas (The Outdoor Nature Club of Houston), 1942 (Box 12)
  - A Field List of Birds of the District of Columbia Region (Audubon Society of District of Columbia), February 1947 (Box 12)
  - "Notes of the Guatemalan Highlands," by Alexander Wetmore (U.S. National Museum, Vol. 89, #3105) (Box 12)
- Miscellany
  - Four photographs with correspondence (Box 12)
  - One divider (Box 12)
  - One strip of six photographs (Box 12)
  - Christmas Census by Leonard Wing, 1900-1939 (Box 12)
  - Drafting compass, MU-2028
  - Pencil, MU-2029
  - Pipe, MU-2030
  - Photograph, International Ornithological Congress in Oxford, 1934 (Map-case 1)